Guide to the Tomie Arai and Legan Wong Papers MSS.439
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series II. Tomie Arai Artwork, 1970-2010; 20 Linear Feet in 25 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 4 oversize flat boxes, and 3 flat-file folders.
  - NYFA (New York Foundation for the Arts) -- Fellowship and Residency, 1990-1995 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations -- China's Bravest Girl -- Correspondence, Promotional Material, Book, 1990-2009 (Box 26, Folder 4-5, Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Illustrations -- New York Asian Women's Center Newsletter,Visions, Printed in English, Chinese and Korean, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Cover Art -- North Star Fund Annual Report, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Chinese y Criollo Collaborative Oral History and Art Project -- Interview Transcripts, Planning Files, Promotional Material, Source Files, 1992-1998 (Box 27, Folder 4-8, Box 28, Folder 1-3)
  - MacDowell Colony Residency, 1993-1994 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Women of Hope: African Americans Who Made a Difference -- Poster Art and Exhibition, 1993-1996 (Box 28, Folder 5, Box 47, Folder 11)
  - Pew Fellowship in the Arts and New York State Regional Initiative -- Panel Member Material, 1993-1997 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - African Burial Ground -- Renewal -- Work Files, 1993-1999 (Box 28, Folder 7, Box 29, Folder 1-4, Box 44, Folder 6)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts -- Advisory Panel Material, 1993-2000 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Cover Art and Proof -- New York Newsday, 1995 (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Illustration -- On the Wings of Peace, 1995 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - MTA Artwork and Exhibition, 1995, 2005 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Nisei Baseball Project, 1996-1998 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Transforming Barbed Wire Arts Project, 1996-1998 (Box 30, Folder 4-7, Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Double Happiness Exhibition -- Interviews, Promotional Material, Catalogue, Planning Notes, 1997-1998 (Box 31, Folder 2-5)
  - NYU Asian / Pacific / American Institute Residency, 1997-1999, 2003-2004 (Box 32, Folder 1, Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Mi Familia Mi Comunidad Exhibition Planning Files, 1997-1999 (Box 32, Folder 2-3, Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Self-Help Graphics Residency -- LA Culture Workshop Promotional Material, Teaching Notes, Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 32, Folder 4-5, Box 33, Folder 1-2)
  - Image of Artwork -- Mural Arts Program Wall Calendar, 2002 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Stories from La Colonia China Exhibition -- Promotional Material, Slides, Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - St. Paul Public School -- Curriculum Aids for Teaching About Minority Women, and Artist (Arai) Profile Poster, undated (Box 33, Folder 4, Box 44, Folder 7)
- Series III. Legan Wong Work Files, 1969-2009; 1970-1990; 7 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 tall manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 flat-file folder.; 2 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
  This series includes material on Legan Wong's work on development of Asian American Studies classes, music production, and his involvement in activist and local cultural organizations in New York in the 1970s and 1980s.
  This series contains source material, lecture notes, course outlines, and correspondence related to Wong's development of college classes on the Asian American experience that he created and taught at Queens College and Hunter College in the 1970s. General research files and conference material on Asian American Studies are also in this series.
  Wong was involved in performance groups in the 1970s and 1980s including Soh Daiko, a folk music drum group, and the Asian Tactical Theater. These files typically include performance programs and schedules, financial reports, promotional material, news clippings, correspondence, notes, and meeting minutes. Wong was also on Team Ronin in the Asian American Softball League of New York in the late 1970s. Team material in this series includes member identification cards with photographs, schedules, correspondence, and rosters.
  This series contains a small amount of files on Wong's involvement in the 1980s as a founding member of East West World Records, which was founded to provide recording opportunities for Asian American artists. These files include concert promotional material, news clippings, letterhead, financial funding, and founding documentation. This series also includes two of the record albums the company produced: Visions, and Back to Back.
  Newsclippings, newsletters, and promotional material for various political groups in which Wong was involved include the Asian Americans for Equal Employment (AAFEE) and Asian in the Spirit of the Indochinese (ASI) are also in this series.
  - Asian American Experience Class -- Source Material, Lecture Plans, Correspondence, Promotional Material, 1969-1976, 1980, undated (Box 33, Folder 7, Box 34, Folder 1-5, Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Asian American-Related Conference Material, 1970-1977 (Box 34, Folder 6-7)
  - Queens College -- Asian American Club, 1971-1972 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Asian American Movement Print Material, 1971-1983 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Asian Tactical Theater, 1972 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - N.Y. Asian Coalition Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Asian American Studies -- City College of New York Controversy, 1972-1974 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Asian Americans for Action -- Newsletter, 1972-1976 (Box 35, Folder 6-7)
  - Asian in the Spirit of the Indochinese (ASI) -- Meeting Notes and Minutes, Event Promotional Material, Informational Booklets, 1973-1974 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Mid-Atlantic Conference on Community Concerns of Asian Americans -- Event Program, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Asian Americans for Equal Employment (AAFEE) -- Clippings, Publications, Event Posters, 1974-1977, 2009 (Box 36, Folder 2, Box 44, Folder 8, Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Asian American Softball League, New York -- Ronin Team Player Cards, League Communications, Schedules, 1978-1979, 1998 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Soh Daiko -- Taiko Performance Group, 1979-1987 (Box 36, Folder 4-6, Box 44, Folder 9)
  - East West World Records -- Clippings, Correspondence, Album Cover Art Proofs, 1982-1991 (Box 36, Folder 7, Box 44, Folder 10-11)
  - East West World Records -- Phonodiscs -- Visions, and Back to Back, 1982-1983 (Box 48, Folder 5-6)
- Series IV. Tomie Arai Early Life and Family, 1937-2006; 1942-1965; 10 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 1 tall manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 4 oversize flat boxes.; 2 Sound_Disc--Vinyl; 1 Sound_Disc--Lacquer
  This series contains materials documenting Arai's early adult life, as well as items created and collected by other family members including her parents, Tim and Tomoe, and her uncle. Arai's school awards, class photographs, and newsletters containing Arai illustrations are mostly from Booker T. Washington Junior High School. Later 1960s photographs of Arai as a young activist are also in this series.
  Record albums from Tim and Tomoe's personal collection in this series include a 1937 Billie Holiday album, a signed copy of the soundtrack for the Broadway show, Flower Drum Song, and Asian American Broadway performer Pat Suzuki's signed album. A history and correspondence related to the New York Buddhist Church in this series relates to the life-long involvement of Arai and her parents in this church community, which also includes photographs from the 1950s of a Bon Odori Festival in Riverside Park. Other items collected by Tim and Tomoe include a print portfolio and newsletters of the Nisei Progressives from the 1950s, publications related to Tim's publication editorial work in the 1940s and 1970s, including a program that also includes Tomie Arai's artwork on the cover.
  Material collected from Arai's parents also include items specifically related to the Japanese American experience during and following World War II in the United States. Items include two Japanese American "yearbook" directories from 1948 and 1949, printed in Japanese and English, one for New York and the other for the entire United States. These directories listed addresses for Japanese individuals which included Tim and Tomoe, and Asian-owned companies. A master's thesis including an interview with Tomoe Arai related to college women and Japanese American wartime incarceration is in this series. Other materials collected by Tomoe Arai include general informational booklets, publications, and articles on the incarceration of Japanese Americans with some specifically related to Tule Lake War Relocation Center and the Granada Relocation Center (also known as Camp Amache), concentration camps in California and Colorado, respectively. Also of note in this series are 15 original watercolor paintings of the Topaz Relocation Center by Arai's paternal uncle, Unosuke Sasahi, which were created during 1943 to 1944 during his incarceration. A 1943 informational booklet on the Granada Relocation Center in Amache, Colorado was given to Tomie Arai's grandparents when they were transferred from the Tule Lake War Relocation Center. Promotional material and schedules from a 1991 pilgrimage event to Tule Lake National Park are also in this series
  - Tim and Tomoe Arai Phonodiscs -- Billie Holiday, Flower Drum Song Soundtrack, and Pat Suzuki's Broadway '59, 1937, 1958-1959 (Box 48, Folder 1-3)
  - A Social Study of the Japanese Population in the Greater New York Area -- Booklet, 1942 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Amache Colorado: Granada Relocation Center -- Orientation Booklet, 1943 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - A Tule Lake Interlude: May 27, 1942- 1943 -- First Anniversary Booklet for Forced Incarceration Camp (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Watercolor Paintings by Unosuke Sasaki -- Topaz Relocation Center, 1943-1944 (Box 45, Item 1-7, Box 46, Folder 1-7, Box 47, Folder 1, Flat-file-folder 1 Left, Flat-file-folder 1 Right)
  - The Displaced Japanese-Americans -- Booklet, circa 1944 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Nisei Vue Magazine -- Tim Arai Article, 1948 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Yearbook / Directory for Japanese Americans -- New York [Printed in English and Japanese], 1948-1949 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Yearbook / Directory for Japanese Americans -- United States [Printed in Japanese], 1949 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Nisei Progressives -- Bandwagon Publication and 15 Japanese Woodcuts, 1950, 1952 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Bon Odori Festival in Riverside Park -- Photographs, circa 1950s (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Tomie Arai School Years-- Yearbooks, Newsletters, Awards, and Photographs, 1962-1965 (Box 37, Folder 9, Box 41, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Tomie Arai in Publications, 1966, 1970, undated (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Chinese National Flag on a Stick -- Used at Rally to Welcome First People's Republic of China Delegation to the U.S., 1971 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Publications Containing Photographs by Nikki Arai, 1971-1975 (Box 37, Folder 11-12, Box 38, Folder 1)
  - NBA-ABA All Star Basketball Classic Program, Editor Tim Arai and Tomie Arai Cover Art, 1972 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Tomie Arai's Daughter Masai in The Electric Company Magazine, 1978 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Tomie Arai Membership Cards and Local New York Business Brochures, 1979, 1996, undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - New York Buddhist Church -- Anniversary Booklet, and Tomoe Arai History Timeline and Letter, 1988, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Tule Lake Pilgrimage Trip Event Material for Tim and Tomoe Arai, and General Redress Research, 1991, 2006 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Honoring Japanese American Veterans of World War II -- Booklet, 1996 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Japanese American Women and the Student Relocation Movement, 1942-1945 -- Thesis Including Tomoe Arai Interview, 1998 (Box 38, Folder 8)